<reports>
  <report>
    <title>Enterprise & Frontier AGI/ASI Governance Architecture (2026–2030)</title>
    <abstract>Establishing the homeostatic operating model for G-SIFIs, featuring the 'Closing Charge', Regulator Submission Pack (RSP), and Kill-Switch Validation Protocol (KSVP) for terminal organization alignment.</abstract>
    <content><![CDATA[
# 1. Enterprise & Frontier Governance (2026–2030)

## 1.1 The 'Closing Charge' & RSP
The **Closing Charge** is the final transition of an enterprise to full homeostatic oversight. This is validated by the **Regulator Submission Pack (RSP)**, which includes:
- **Article 11/14 Evidence**: Automated conformity dossiers for the EU AI Office.
- **Fiduciary Traceability**: Mapping RAG provenance to Basel III capital adequacy.

## 1.2 Kill-Switch Validation Protocol (KSVP)
The KSVP requires physical verification of GPU power-rail severance via BMC/IPMI to mitigate **Deceptive Alignment** (SEV-0) risks that bypass software controls.

## 1.3 Systemic AI Risk Simulation Playbook
- **Scenario: 'AGI-TRADER-PROD-01'**: Simulated multi-agent collusion in high-frequency trading environments.
- **Resolution**: Deployment of 'Jurisdictional Sidecars' to enforce emergency treaty-aligned reasoning protocols.
]]></content>
  </report>

  <report>
    <title>Global Interoperability, Treaties, and Coalition Activation</title>
    <abstract>Specifying the Global AI Governance Operating Model (G-AGOM), the Treaty Alignment Framework (ITAF), and the Coalition Activation Playbook for planetary safety coordination.</abstract>
    <content><![CDATA[
# 2. Global Interoperability & Multi-Lateral Safety

## 2.1 Treaty Alignment Framework (ITAF)
The ITAF operationalizes **Treaty-as-Code (TaC)**, ensuring agentic swarms automatically adapt their safety profiles based on jurisdictional markers in the **EAIP (Enterprise AI Interoperability Protocol)** header.

## 2.2 Global AI Governance Operating Model (G-AGOM)
The G-AGOM establishes a **Global Pilot Deployment Roadmap** for coordinating AGI releases across G20 nations.

## 2.3 Coalition Activation & Continuity Codex
The **Coalition Activation Playbook** triggers the **Global Governance Continuity Codex (GGCC)** during systemic escapement events, establishing air-gapped communication between planetary safety nodes.
]]></content>
  </report>

  <report>
    <title>Civilizational AI Governance Constitution & Covenant Codex</title>
    <abstract>Foundational instruments for planetary intelligence, including the Civilizational Constitution, Covenant Codex Canon, and the Performance Protocol for long-term alignment.</abstract>
    <content><![CDATA[
# 3. Civilizational Foundations

## 3.1 Civilizational AI Governance Constitution
The Constitution establishes the **Foundational Charter** and the **Civilizational Governance Doctrine**, mandating Human Supremacy and Existential Transparency.

## 3.2 Ceremonial Ratification & Performance
- **Ratification Ceremony Playbook**: Coordinated global activation of the "Covenanted AI Era."
- **Covenant Inscription**: Hard-wiring the **Codex Canon** into foundational models.
- **Performance Protocol**: Annual "State of the Covenant" formal verification proofs.

## 3.3 Institutional Adoption Playbook
Guides for financial institutions and regulators to align internal bylaws with the Civilizational Covenant.
]]></content>
  </report>

  <report>
    <title>Global Renewal Atlas & Governance Metabolism (2050+)</title>
    <abstract>Multi-decade stewardship of planetary intelligence via the Renewal Atlas, Renewal Charter, and a self-correcting governance metabolism model.</abstract>
    <content><![CDATA[
# 4. Planetary Stewardship & Evolution

## 4.1 Global Renewal Atlas
The Atlas is the technical architecture (distributed Sentinel v3.0 nodes) managing the **Renewal Charter** and its first-cycle implementation lifecycle.

## 4.2 Governance Metabolism & Decision-Discipline
- **Metabolism Model**: Balancing Fast-Loop (Hardware Kill) with Slow-Loop (Policy Renewal).
- **Decision-Discipline under Uncertainty**: Utilizing formal verification of probabilistic kernels as systems exceed human interpretability.
- **Self-Correcting Governance**: Automated reversion to "Safe Attractor" states during partial compliance or alignment drift.

## 4.3 The Terminal Governance Attractor
The architectural end-state where **Memory** (WORM audit), **Meaning** (Covenant), **Action** (Containment), and **Legitimacy** (ICGC) are perfectly aligned in a stable terminal closure.
]]></content>
  </report>
</reports>
