<report>
  <title>Enterprise AI Agent Interoperability Protocol (EAIP) v1.0: Technical Specification</title>
  <abstract>This specification establishes a high-rigor technical framework for standardized agent-to-agent (A2A) synchronization in distributed enterprise environments. EAIP mandates gRPC for low-latency binary transport, leverages SPIFFE/SPIRE for decentralized machine identity (SVIDs/mTLS), and implements the Recursive Context Envelope (RCE) to ensure deterministic state handoffs and safety invariants across autonomous workflows.</abstract>
  <content><![CDATA[
# 1. Necessity of Standardization

The transition from isolated Large Language Model (LLM) chat interfaces to distributed agentic ecosystems necessitates a standardized interoperability layer. Standardization via EAIP is driven by the following technical and business imperatives:

- **Protocol Fragmentation:** Current ad-hoc JSON-over-HTTP integrations lead to non-deterministic failure modes and unmanageable integration surfaces as agent swarms scale.
- **Auditability and Traceability:** Regulatory regimes (e.g., EU AI Act, GDPR Art. 22) require a non-repudiable "Chain of Thought" and "Chain of Custody" for all data processed by autonomous entities.
- **Latency Optimization:** Multi-agent chains are primarily bottlenecked by serialization overhead. Standardized binary protocols are required for sub-millisecond execution in transaction-critical environments.
- **Safety Invariants:** A common protocol allows for the injection of global safety gates (e.g., spending limits, PII redaction) at the transport layer rather than the application layer.

# 2. API Architecture: Comparative Analysis and Recommendation

Agentic workflows require high-frequency, small-payload interactions with complex state dependencies and bidirectional telemetry.

| Feature | REST (JSON) | WebSockets | gRPC (Protobuf) |
| :--- | :--- | :--- | :--- |
| **Transport** | HTTP/1.1 or 2 | TCP / HTTP Upgrade | **HTTP/2** |
| **Serialization** | Textual (UTF-8) | Binary or Text | **Binary (Protobuf)** |
| **Serialization Overhead** | High (Field repetition) | Low | **Ultra-Low (Indexed)** |
| **Latency Cost** | High (Parsing) | Low (Stream) | **Ultra-Low (Binary)** |
| **Contract Safety** | Optional (OpenAPI) | N/A | **Mandatory (.proto)** |
| **Streaming** | Unidirectional (SSE) | Full-Duplex | **Full Duplex / Multiplexed** |

**Definitive Recommendation: gRPC.**
EAIP mandates gRPC as the transport substrate. Binary serialization via Protocol Buffers ensures minimal payload size, while HTTP/2 multiplexing allows concurrent agent sub-tasks over a single connection without head-of-line blocking. The strict `.proto` definitions act as a compile-time safety contract for agentic tool-calling interfaces.

# 3. IAM for Autonomous Agents: SPIFFE/SPIRE Implementation

Traditional OAuth2/OIDC flows are insufficient for sub-second, machine-to-machine autonomous identity. EAIP leverages **SPIFFE/SPIRE** for decentralized identity management:

- **Identity Issuance:** Each agent is issued a **SPIFFE ID** (e.g., `spiffe://prod.acme.com/agent/treasury-bot`) anchored to a short-lived **SVID** (X.509 certificate).
- **Mutual TLS (mTLS):** All EAIP traffic MUST be encrypted and authenticated via Mutual TLS using SVIDs, ensuring peer-to-peer authentication without long-lived secret exfiltration.
- **Workload Attestation:** The SPIRE server performs "Node Attestation" and "Workload Attestation" (e.g., binary hash, Kubernetes namespace, TPM measurements) before issuing identity, ensuring only authorized, untampered agent logic can participate in the fabric.

# 4. State & Error Management: Protocols for Coherence

Distributed reasoning requires a standardized mechanism for state preservation and deterministic recovery.

- **Recursive Context Envelope (RCE):** Every gRPC call must include an RCE metadata header containing a Merkle-linked trace of previous reasoning steps and signed resource constraints (e.g., token budgets). This prevents "Context Drift."
- **Context Handoffs:** When Agent A delegates a sub-task to Agent B, the RCE is updated with Agent A's reasoning hash and the current intent. Agent B must validate this trace against the Epistemic Ledger before execution.
- **Error Recovery and Fallbacks:**
    - **Circuit Breakers:** If an agent's "Deception Index" (calculated via internal consistency probing) exceeds a pre-defined threshold, the EAIP bridge trips, halting all outbound tool-calls.
    - **Symbolic Fallback:** Upon gRPC `DEADLINE_EXCEEDED` or `INTERNAL` errors, the system MUST revert to a pre-defined symbolic heuristic (rule-based logic) to prevent "Agent Deadlock."

# 5. Reference Architecture Diagram: Agent-to-Agent Handoff

```mermaid
sequenceDiagram
    participant OA as Orchestrator Agent
    participant IAM as SPIRE Server (mTLS)
    participant SA as Specialist Agent (gRPC)
    participant EL as Epistemic Audit Ledger

    OA->>IAM: Attest Workload & Request SVID
    IAM-->>OA: Issue SVID (X.509)

    Note over OA: Construct RCE (State + Trace)

    OA->>SA: gRPC Call: ProcessSubTask(RCE)
    Note over SA: Validate mTLS + RCE Signature

    alt Policy Success
        SA->>SA: Reasoning & Tool-Execution
        SA-->>OA: Task Result (Updated RCE)
        OA->>EL: Anchor Handoff Hash (Immutable)
    else Policy Breach
        SA-->>OA: gRPC Error: FAILED_PRECONDITION
        OA->>EL: Alert: Safety Interlock Tripped
    end
```
]]></content>
</report>
