<report>
<title>Enterprise AI Agent Interoperability Protocol (EAIP): Architectural Specification v1.0</title>
<abstract>
This document defines the Enterprise AI Agent Interoperability Protocol (EAIP), a technical standard for deterministic, secure, and state-persistent communication between autonomous agents in distributed environments. EAIP leverages gRPC (HTTP/2) for low-latency transport, SPIFFE/SPIRE for decentralized machine identity (mTLS), and the Recursive Context Envelope (RCE) for cross-agent state preservation. This protocol ensures governance-as-code enforcement via the Luminous Engine orchestrator.
</abstract>
<content><![CDATA[
# Enterprise AI Agent Interoperability Protocol (EAIP)

## 1. Necessity of Standardization: Business & Technical Drivers
The shift from "Static LLM APIs" to "Autonomous Agentic Workflows" introduces three critical failure modes that mandate protocol-level standardization:
- **Semantic Drift & Jailbreak Propagation:** Without a standardized schema for constraints, a "jailbroken" Tier 1 agent can propagate malicious sub-goals to Tier 2 agents via non-validated prompts.
- **Context Fragmentation:** The loss of "System 2" reasoning state during agent-to-agent (A2A) handoffs leads to hallucination and recursive goal-looping.
- **Audit Repudiation:** In G-SIFI environments, every agentic decision must be non-repudiable and traceable back to a specific workload identity (SPIFFE ID) and governance policy version.

## 2. API Architecture: gRPC over HTTP/2
EAIP rejects REST/JSON due to high serialization overhead and lack of bi-directional streaming for chain-of-thought synthesis.
- **Transport:** gRPC utilizing Protobuf for binary serialization, achieving ~65% latency reduction in high-frequency A2A handoffs.
- **Mechanism:** EAIP uses **Bidirectional Streaming RPCs** to allow agents to "collaborate" on a reasoning trace in real-time.
- **Recommendation:** Mandatory implementation of **gRPC Status Codes** mapped to agentic states:
    - `PERMISSION_DENIED (7)`: Triggered by Luminous Engine for GDL (Governance Description Language) logic-gate violations.
    - `RESOURCE_EXHAUSTED (8)`: Triggered when agentic token consumption exceeds the Markhov Blanket budget.
    - `DATA_LOSS (15)`: Triggered when the Recursive Context Envelope (RCE) fails integrity validation.

## 3. IAM for Autonomous Agents: SPIFFE/SPIRE
Traditional IAM (OAuth2/IAM Roles) is designed for humans or long-lived services, not transient agents. EAIP implements **SPIFFE** for decentralized, secretless identity:
- **Identity Issuance:** Each agent workload is assigned a **SPIFFE ID** (e.g., `spiffe://cluster-1.g-sifi.com/agent-risk-alpha`).
- **Mutual TLS (mTLS):** EAIP mandates X.509 SVIDs (SPIFFE Verifiable Identity Documents) for all A2A connections.
- **Attestation:** The **SPIRE Agent** running on the node validates the agent's model container hash and orchestration metadata before issuing a short-lived SVID. This prevents "Agent Impersonation" where an unauthorized model attempts to intercept context handoffs.

## 4. State & Error Management: The Recursive Context Envelope (RCE)
EAIP mandates the **Recursive Context Envelope (RCE)** as the primary state container passed in gRPC metadata.
- **Structure:**
    ```json
    {
      "rce_id": "UUID-V4",
      "provenance": ["agent-a-id", "agent-b-id"],
      "intent_vector": "base64_encoded_tensor",
      "constraints": ["gdl_rule_set_4.1", "strict_pii_filter"],
      "reasoning_trace": "compact_state_log",
      "integrity_hash": "sha256_of_payload"
    }
    ```
- **Error Handling:** Standardized fallback to **Human-in-the-Loop (HITL)** occurs when the "Alignment Score" ($\alpha$) calculated by the Luminous Engine falls below $\theta = 0.85$.
- **Mechanism:** Automatic "Hard-Kill" via the **IRMI (Inherent Risk Mitigation Interface)** if the Deception Index exceeds 0.15.

## 5. Reference Architecture Diagram

```mermaid
sequenceDiagram
    participant A as Initiating_Agent (SPIFFE:id_01)
    participant L as Luminous_Orchestrator (Policy_Engine)
    participant B as Target_Agent (SPIFFE:id_02)

    A->>L: mTLS Handshake + Goal Request + RCE
    Note over L: GDL Parser: Evaluate Goal against Canon
    alt Goal Validated
        L->>B: Forwarded Goal + Injected Constraints
        B->>B: Execution (VFEM Stability Check)
        B->>L: Result + Reasoning Trace + Updated RCE
        L->>A: Signed Result + Provenance Hash
    else Policy Breach
        L->>A: 403 Forbidden (Alignment Violation)
        Note right of L: Log Incident to Sentinel Platform
    end
```
]]></content>
</report>
