<report>
<title>Enterprise AI Agent Interoperability Protocol (EAIP) v1.0</title>
<abstract>This specification establishes a standardized communication and governance framework for autonomous agents within the enterprise. It mandates gRPC for high-concurrency transport, SPIFFE/SPIRE for decentralized identity attestation, and a recursive context envelope model for robust state preservation and error handling across multi-agent handoffs.</abstract>
<content><![CDATA[# 1. Necessity of Standardization

The proliferation of autonomous agents in the enterprise has created a landscape of siloed "agentic islands," where disparate LLM-backed systems operate using incompatible communication patterns and inconsistent state management. This fragmentation leads to high semantic entropy, significant vendor lock-in, and an inability to enforce deterministic governance across multi-agent workflows. Standardization is technically driven by the need for low-latency, type-safe inter-agent messaging and the requirement for cryptographically verifiable identity. From a business perspective, the Enterprise AI Agent Interoperability Protocol (EAIP) mitigates the risk of non-deterministic failure in critical paths by providing a predictable, auditable handoff mechanism that ensures context integrity and prevents systemic goal-drift.

# 2. API Architecture

Effective agentic communication requires high-concurrency, bidirectional data flows that exceed the capabilities of traditional unary patterns.

### Comparative Analysis:
*   **REST (HTTP/1.1):** Characterized by high header overhead and a synchronous, request-response paradigm. REST is poorly suited for the high-frequency state synchronization required by agents, as its lack of multiplexing introduces unacceptable latency in complex mesh topologies.
*   **WebSockets:** While providing bidirectional streaming, WebSockets lack a native schema-enforcement layer. In an enterprise environment, the absence of a strict contract often results in runtime parsing errors and an inability to maintain semantic consistency across heterogeneous agents.
*   **gRPC (HTTP/2):** gRPC utilizes Protocol Buffers (Protobuf) for binary serialization, resulting in a 5x-10x reduction in payload size compared to JSON. Its support for bidirectional streaming and multiplexing enables real-time "thinking-aloud" protocols and synchronous state locking.

**Recommendation:** EAIP mandates **gRPC** as the transport layer. The use of Protobuf ensures rigorous type-safety and allows for the generation of client/server stubs across multiple languages, facilitating a polyglot agent ecosystem.

# 3. IAM for Autonomous Agents

Legacy IAM strategies involving long-lived API keys or static credentials are insufficient for autonomous workloads. EAIP leverages the **SPIFFE (Secure Production Identity Framework for Everyone)** standard to provide machine-identity-as-a-service.

*   **Identity Provider (SPIRE):** Every agent must register with a SPIRE server to obtain an **X.509 SVID** (SPIFFE Verifiable Identity Document). Identity is established through workload attestation (e.g., verifying binary hashes, container metadata, or cloud provider signatures).
*   **Authentication:** Mutual TLS (mTLS) is enforced for all gRPC connections. Agents verify peer identities by validating the SAN (Subject Alternative Name) field in the presented SVID.
*   **Authorization:** EAIP integrates **Open Policy Agent (OPA)** for fine-grained, attribute-based access control (ABAC). Agents query the OPA Sidecar to determine if a specific Peer identity (SPIFFE-ID) is authorized to perform an action (e.g., `READ_CONTEXT`, `EXECUTE_TOOL`) based on dynamic policy-as-code.

# 4. State & Error Management

To preserve the multi-agent reasoning chain, EAIP introduces the **Recursive Context Envelope (RCE)**.

### Context Handoff Protocol:
The RCE is a Protobuf message containing:
1.  **Trace ID:** Aligned with W3C Traceparent for distributed observability.
2.  **Memory Stack:** A summary of previous agent outputs to prevent token-limit overflow.
3.  **Safe Boundary Manifest:** A list of permitted tools and resource constraints (e.g., `MAX_RECURSION=5`).

### Standardized Error Taxonomy:
Agents must respond with specific gRPC status codes to prevent cascading failures:
| Code | Meaning | Handoff Strategy |
| :--- | :--- | :--- |
| `0x101` | Context Overflow | Initiate recursive summarization of RCE and retry once. |
| `0x102` | Policy Block | OPA denied action; log to governance dashboard and return to controller. |
| `0x103` | Agentic Loop | Detected cyclic request; terminate and trigger manual human-in-the-loop fallback. |
| `0x104` | Tool Failure | Systemic exception in tool execution; agent should attempt one self-correction before reporting. |

# 5. Reference Architecture Diagram

The following sequence diagram details a standardized handoff between two autonomous agents within the EAIP mesh.

```mermaid
sequenceDiagram
    participant A as Agent Alpha
    participant S as "SPIRE Server"
    participant B as Agent Beta
    participant O as "OPA Engine"

    A->>S: Request SVID
    S-->>A: X.509 SVID
    A->>B: gRPC Request (RCE Payload)
    B->>S: Validate Peer SVID
    S-->>B: Peer Identity Verified
    B->>O: Evaluate ABAC Policy
    O-->>B: Action ALLOW
    B-->>A: gRPC Response (Updated RCE)
```]]></content>
</report>
