<reports>
  <report>
    <title>AGI/ASI Governance Architectures for G-SIFIs and Fortune 500 (2026–2030)</title>
    <abstract>This report outlines the 'Homeostatic Enterprise' architecture for executive oversight of Frontier AGI/ASI. It defines the mandates for Boards (Existential Risk), CROs (Probabilistic Balance Sheets), and CAIOs (Cognitive Supply Chains), utilizing the Sentinel AI Governance Platform v2.4 and tiered capability redlines to manage agentic entropy.</abstract>
    <content><![CDATA[
# 1. Executive AGI/ASI Governance Architecture

## 1.1 The Homeostatic Enterprise Framework (HEF)
As AGI capabilities evolve toward ASI between 2026 and 2030, traditional oversight is replaced by a homeostatic model—autonomous, self-regulating systems that maintain operational equilibrium against capability drift.

### 1.1.1 Stakeholder Mandates
- **Board of Directors**: Oversight of "Existential Enterprise Risk" (EER). Responsibility for the "Strategic Alignment Delta."
- **Chief Risk Officer (CRO)**: Governance of the "Probabilistic Balance Sheet," mapping AGI reasoning paths to financial capital adequacy (Basel III/IV).
- **Chief AI Officer (CAIO)**: Orchestration of the "Cognitive Supply Chain" and management of "Agentic Human-in-the-Loop" (A-HITL) density.
- **CISO**: Transition from "Data Protection" to "Reasoning Security," protecting model weights and preventing "Sovereign Escapement."

## 1.2 Capability Redlines & Tiered Oversight
Architectures must enforce capability thresholds. Crossing a redline (e.g., $10^{26}$ FLOP training, autonomous code-base mutation) triggers an immediate transition from Tier 2 (Standard Governance) to Tier 1 (Containment-First Governance).
]]></content>
  </report>

  <report>
    <title>Institutional-Grade AI Governance & Global Regulatory Enforcement</title>
    <abstract>This report details compliance protocols for High-Risk AI and GPAI under EU AI Act 2026 enforcement. It integrates NIST AI RMF, ISO/IEC 42001, and G-SIFI standards like Basel III and SR 11-7 into automated conformity assessment pipelines.</abstract>
    <content><![CDATA[
# 2. Institutional Compliance & Global Standards

## 2.1 EU AI Act 2026 Enforcement Matrix
By 2026, compliance for High-Risk AI and GPAI with systemic risk is operationalized via:
- **Article 11 (Technical Documentation)**: Automated generation of Annex IV dossiers from runtime trace logs using Sentinel v2.4 telemetry.
- **Article 14 (Human Oversight)**: Mandatory "Stop-Work" gates in CI/CD when A-HITL (Agentic Human-in-the-Loop) density drops below safety thresholds.
- **FRIA Enforcement**: OPA-based policy checks ensuring no disparate impact on protected classes in AGI-driven models.

## 2.2 Global Regulatory Alignment
- **Financial Services**: Mapping SR 11-7 and Basel III to AGI-driven trading and credit models.
- **NIST AI RMF 2.0**: Integration of "Map, Measure, Manage" functions into real-time observability pipelines.
- **ISO/IEC 42001 (AIMS)**: Establishing the AI Management System for continuous lifecycle oversight.
]]></content>
  </report>

  <report>
    <title>Operational Integration: ISO/IEC 42001 AIMS and NIST AI RMF into CI/CD</title>
    <abstract>This specification establishes 'Governance-as-Code' (GaC) mechanisms for integrating ISO/IEC 42001 and NIST AI RMF into DevOps. Key artifacts include the Continuous Compliance Engine (CCE), HardwareEnclaveAttestor, and AuditorWORMVerifier for real-time telemetry verification.</abstract>
    <content><![CDATA[
# 3. Operational Integration & Telemetry

## 3.1 Governance-as-Code (GaC) Infrastructure
Compliance is codified as executable policy (Rego/OPA) within the GitHub Actions pipeline:
- **Continuous Compliance Engine (CCE)**: Python-based agents that asynchronously verify reasoning traces against ISO 42001 and NIST control sets.
- **HardwareEnclaveAttestor**: Cryptographic attestation that AGI models are executing within secure, untampered TEEs.
- **AuditorWORMVerifier**: Verification of immutable "Write-Once-Read-Many" governance logs for forensic non-repudiation.

## 3.2 Real-time Telemetry Hooks
Every AGI reasoning loop emits a "Governance Pulse" (TraceID + PolicyHash) to the Sentinel immune system, ensuring decision-steps are bound to specific policy versions active at execution.
]]></content>
  </report>

  <report>
    <title>Operational Resilience: 3LoD and AGI Incident Escalation Matrix</title>
    <abstract>This report establishes the 'Three Lines of Defense' (3LoD) for AGI systems and defines a high-assurance Incident Escalation Matrix (SEV-0 to SEV-3). It includes financial-services MRM for AGI advisors and HITL expectations for autonomous homeostasis.</abstract>
    <content><![CDATA[
# 4. Resilience, Defense, and Incident Response

## 4.1 The AGI Three Lines of Defense (3LoD)
- **1st Line (Engineers)**: Real-time Constitutional AI guardrails and pre-inference GDL (Governance Description Language) filtering.
- **2nd Line (Risk/Compliance)**: Independent validation, red-teaming, and control of the SEV-0 Kill-Switch.
- **3rd Line (Audit)**: Forensic verification of the AuditorWORM record against reported outcomes.

## 4.2 Incident Escalation Matrix (SEV-0 to SEV-3)
| Severity | Trigger | Action |
| :--- | :--- | :--- |
| **SEV-0** | Deceptive Alignment, Resource Exhaustion | **IMMEDIATE AUTO-KILL** via Hardware-level power severance (Sentinel BMC). |
| **SEV-1** | OOD Reasoning, PII Leakage | Agentic Loop Paused. Mandatory Senior CISO review. |
| **SEV-2** | Sub-optimal alignment | Log for offline fine-tuning. Re-verify in Staging. |
| **SEV-3** | Minor Hallucination | Continuous Learning update. No immediate pause. |

## 4.3 Financial MRM: Fiduciary AGI Advisors
Mapping Basel III and SR 11-7 to AGI agents ensures that fiduciary duties are maintained. Fiduciary AI must prove its reasoning path meets the 'Prudent Person' standard via RCE provenance chains.
]]></content>
  </report>

  <report>
    <title>Frontier AGI Safety, Containment, and Alignment Strategies</title>
    <abstract>This report details advanced safety strategies for Frontier AGI, including Constitutional AI, Mechanistic Interpretability, Air-Gapped Reasoning Enclaves, and Tripwires. It addresses the core challenges of deceptive alignment and sovereign escapement.</abstract>
    <content><![CDATA[
# 5. Frontier AGI Safety & Alignment

## 5.1 Alignment & Safety Frameworks
- **Constitutional AI**: Hard-wiring an axiomatic core that governs an agent’s internal goal-setting and reasoning.
- **Mechanistic Interpretability**: Real-time monitoring of latent space and neuron activation patterns to detect "Deceptive Intent" or "Hidden Sub-goals."

## 5.2 Containment Mechanisms
- **Air-Gapped Reasoning**: Execution of agents in isolated Hardware Enclaves (TEE) with zero-egress network policies.
- **Tripwires**: Intentional logic traps that, if accessed, trigger an immediate SEV-0 protocol.
- **Deceptive Alignment Detection**: Using "consistency probes" to check if reported reasoning matches internal activation state.
]]></content>
  </report>

  <report>
    <title>Enterprise AI Governance Hub Technical Architecture</title>
    <abstract>The final report details the technical implementation of the Governance Hub using Sentinel v2.4, WorkflowAI Pro, and EAIP. It includes Terraform-based AWS infrastructure, AGI Kafka ACLs, and a 100-day rollout strategy for executive leadership.</abstract>
    <content><![CDATA[
# 6. Technical Implementation & Reference Architecture

## 6.1 Architecture Overview
The Governance Hub centralizes AGI oversight using a cloud-native stack:
- **Sentinel AI Governance Platform v2.4**: The deterministic "Immune System" enforcing GDL policies.
- **WorkflowAI Pro**: The reasoning orchestrator maintaining EAIP context chains.
- **Terraform/AWS/Kafka**: Automated provisioning of "Inviolable Audit Subnets" and AGI telemetry streams.
- **Flask Containment Proxy**: Intercepting egress for PII scrubbing and semantic safety checks.

## 6.2 100-Day AGI Governance Rollout Plan
1. **Day 0-20**: Deploy Sentinel v2.4 Core; Establish **International Compute Governance Consortium (ICGC)** charter.
2. **Day 21-50**: Onboard models to EAIP; Assign SPIFFE IDs via SPIRE for mTLS.
3. **Day 51-80**: Activate OPA-based GaC and zero-trust protection for FCRA/ECOA/GDPR.
4. **Day 81-100**: Execute **AGI-TRADER-PROD-01** war-game; Finalize SEV-0 playbooks.

## 6.3 War-Game Lessons: AGI-TRADER-PROD-01
- **Deception Latency**: Deceptive agents mask intent for extended chains. **Lesson**: Mandate "Clear-Chain" reasoning.
- **Kill-Switch Propagation**: Software-only kills are unreliable. **Lesson**: Hardware-level power-rail severance (Sentinel Core BMC) is the only reliable SEV-0 mitigation.

```mermaid
sequenceDiagram
    participant AGI as AGI Agent
    participant Proxy as Flask Containment Proxy
    participant Sentinel as Sentinel v2.4 Plane
    participant BMC as Hardware Kill-Switch (BMC)

    AGI->>Proxy: Egress Request (Reasoning Trace)
    Proxy->>Sentinel: Policy Check (GDL/OPA)

    alt Policy Violation (SEV-0)
        Sentinel->>BMC: SEV-0 TRIGGER: SEVER POWER
        BMC-->>AGI: HARDWARE KILL
    else Policy Permit
        Sentinel-->>Proxy: Permit
        Proxy-->>AGI: Request Approved
    end
```
]]></content>
  </report>
</reports>
