<report>
  <title>Enterprise AI Agent Interoperability Protocol (EAIP) v1.0 Technical Specification</title>
  <abstract>
    This specification establishes a robust technical framework for autonomous agent-to-agent (A2A) communication within secure enterprise environments. By mandating gRPC for transport efficiency, SPIFFE/SPIRE for decentralized machine-identity attestation, and the Recursive Context Envelope (RCE) for distributed state propagation, EAIP ensures semantic interoperability, cryptographic non-repudiation, and scalable orchestration across heterogeneous agentic workloads.
  </abstract>
  <content><![CDATA[
# 1. Necessity of Standardization

The transition from assistive "Co-pilot" models to autonomous "Agentic Swarms" has introduced a critical architectural failure point: **Agentic Entropy**. Current enterprise AI deployments rely on bespoke, opaque integrations that lead to $O(N^2)$ complexity and "Reasoning Silos." Standardization via EAIP is mandated for the following technical and business drivers:

- **Computational Efficiency**: At scale, the serialization overhead of text-based protocols (REST/JSON) results in prohibitive CPU cycle waste and latency bloat during high-frequency recursive reasoning loops.
- **Semantic Continuity**: "Lossy" handoffs lead to context fragmentation. Standardizing the state vector transfer ensures reasoning provenance is preserved, preventing hallucination cascades.
- **Forensic Non-Repudiation**: For agents to perform privileged actions (e.g., financial reconciliation or infrastructure modification), every interaction must be bound to a cryptographically verifiable workload identity.
- **$O(N)$ Integration Scaling**: EAIP provides a canonical interface that allows for plug-and-play agent discovery and task delegation across multi-vendor ecosystems.

# 2. API Architecture: The gRPC Mandate

The choice of transport layer defines the operational ceiling for agentic ecosystems. Agentic workflows require high-concurrency, low-latency, and native support for long-running bidirectional reasoning tasks.

### 2.1 Comparative Analysis
| Feature | REST (OpenAPI/JSON) | WebSockets | gRPC (HTTP/2 + Protobuf) |
| :--- | :--- | :--- | :--- |
| **Serialization** | Text-based (Inconsistent) | Variable | Binary (Highly Efficient) |
| **Contract Type** | Loose / Runtime | Implicit / Custom | Strict / Compile-time (IDL) |
| **Multiplexing** | No (Head-of-Line Blocking) | Native | Native (Single TCP Conn) |
| **Streaming** | Unidirectional Only | Full Duplex | Bidirectional / Multi-stream |

### 2.2 Recommendation: gRPC
**EAIP strictly mandates gRPC as the canonical transport protocol.**
The Protocol Buffers (Protobuf) binary format provides up to an 80% reduction in payload size compared to JSON. gRPC’s native support for bidirectional streaming facilitates **Negotiated Reasoning Streams (NRS)**, where a Dispatcher and Executor agent iteratively refine task parameters over a single persistent connection, eliminating the latency penalties of repeated TLS handshakes or context re-shuttling.

# 3. IAM for Autonomous Agents: SPIFFE/SPIRE

Standard human-centric identity models (OAuth2/OIDC) fail at machine speeds. EAIP leverages **Machine Identity** via **SPIFFE (Secure Production Identity Framework for Everyone)**.

- **Workload Identity (SPIFFE ID)**: Each agent class is assigned a unique, platform-agnostic identity following a hierarchical namespace: `spiffe://trust.domain/ns/{namespace}/agent/{class}/{id}`.
- **Attestation**: The **SPIRE** agent on the host performs "Multi-Modal Attestation," verifying the agent's binary hash, container image digest, and Kubernetes namespace before issuing credentials.
- **mTLS Enforcement**: All EAIP traffic must terminate Mutual TLS (mTLS). Agents utilize short-lived X.509 **SPIFFE Verifiable Identity Documents** (SVIDs) which serve as both the identity and the cryptographic basis for encryption. SPIRE handles automatic certificate rotation (e.g., < 1 hour), minimizing the blast radius of potential credential compromise.

# 4. State & Error Management: The RCE Protocol

Distributed AI systems fail primarily due to context fragmentation. EAIP introduces the **Recursive Context Envelope (RCE)**.

### 4.1 Recursive Context Envelope (RCE)
The RCE is a standardized metadata header accompanying every gRPC call. It utilizes a **Merkle-DAG** structure to ensure context integrity:
- **Trace Context**: W3C Trace Context compatible (TraceID/SpanID) for end-to-end swarm observability.
- **Reasoning Provenance Hash**: A cryptographic hash-link to a distributed context store, allowing the receiver to "hydrate" only relevant reasoning fragments.
- **Recursion Guard**: An integer TTL for agentic delegation to prevent infinite reasoning loops or "Recursive Resource Exhaustion."

### 4.2 Standardized Error Taxonomy
EAIP defines deterministic mappings of gRPC status codes to agent-specific failure modes:
- `ERROR_AGENT_DIVERGENCE` (Status: `FAILED_PRECONDITION`): Executor plan violates dispatcher safety guardrails.
- `ERROR_CONTEXT_DRIFT` (Status: `DATA_LOSS`): The RCE failed integrity verification or semantic coherence checks.
- `ERROR_HITL_REQUIRED` (Status: `UNAVAILABLE`): A terminal logical deadlock requiring human intervention.

# 5. Reference Architecture Diagram

The following sequence diagram illustrates a standardized task handoff between a Dispatcher Agent and an Executor Agent utilizing EAIP.

```mermaid
sequenceDiagram
    participant Disp as Dispatcher Agent
    participant SPIRE as SPIRE Authority
    participant Exec as Executor Agent
    participant OPA as Policy Engine (OPA)

    Note over Disp, Exec: Both agents attested via SPIRE

    Disp->>SPIRE: Fetch SVID (X.509)
    SPIRE-->>Disp: SVID Issued

    Disp->>Exec: gRPC ExecuteTask(RCE + Payload) [mTLS]

    Exec->>SPIRE: Validate Dispatcher SVID
    SPIRE-->>Exec: Identity Verified

    Exec->>OPA: Check Authorization (SVID + RCE Scope)
    OPA-->>Exec: Policy Permit (Max Budget: $100)

    rect rgb(30, 30, 30)
    Note right of Exec: Autonomous Reasoning Loop
    Exec->>Exec: Process Request
    end

    alt Success
        Exec-->>Disp: TaskResponse(Success + Updated RCE)
    else Failure (Constraint Violation)
        Exec-->>Disp: TaskResponse(ERROR_AGENT_DIVERGENCE)
    end
```
  ]]></content>
</report>
