<report>
<title>Institutional AGI/ASI Governance: Unified Blueprint and Strategic Reference (2026–2030)</title>
<abstract>This blueprint establishes the definitive technical and strategic framework for Global Systemically Important Financial Institutions (GSIFIs) to manage the transition to AGI. It synthesizes establish prudential mandates (Basel III, SR 11-7) with modern AI regulations through a defense-in-depth architecture. Key technical implementations include Kafka ACL governance, sidecar-based OPA policy enforcement, and WORM-locked evidence storage. The report details global safety pillars (G-Series) and frontier safety strategies (Cognitive Resonance) required for regulator-ready institutional stability in the autonomous intelligence era.</abstract>
<content><![CDATA[

$(cat COMPENDIUM_STRATEGIC_PILLARS.md)

$(cat REGULATORY_ALIGNMENT.md)

$(cat COMPENDIUM_TRUST_STACK.md)

$(cat GSIFI_TECHNICAL_IMPL.md)

$(cat COMPENDIUM_GLOBAL_GOVERNANCE.md)

# Part IV: Implementation Roadmap and Auditor Workflows

## 1. 30/60/90-Day GSIFI Rollout
- **Day 30**: Establishment of the CAIGO root-of-trust and Sentinel Registry activation.
- **Day 60**: Deployment of SPIFFE/SPIRE attestation for all production trading models.
- **Day 90**: Mandatory WORM evidence logging for all high-risk financial decisions.

## 2. Auditor Verification Protocols
Auditors operate "Validation Swarms" that periodically ingest evidence bundles from WORM storage.
- **Drift Audit**: Comparing the weights-hash in the evidence bundle against the "Approved Registry" to detect unauthorized model swapping.
- **Logic Audit**: Re-executing reasoning traces in an isolated sandbox to verify that the agent's internal monologue matches the external tool-call outcomes.

# Conclusion
The professionalization of AGI governance in GSIFIs requires moving beyond ethical principles to deterministic infrastructure controls. By integrating SPIRE identity, OPA policy-as-code, and Kafka auditability, institutions can achieve a regulator-ready "Substrate of Trust" capable of supporting autonomous superhuman intelligence.

]]></content>
</report>
