<report>
<title>The Terminal Governance Attractor: Aligning Memory, Meaning, and Action</title>
<abstract>This final report synthesizes the end-to-end civilizational AI governance stack (2026–2050+). It explains how the integration of enterprise architecture, global treaties, and civilizational constitutions establishes AI governance as regulated critical infrastructure, aligning with NIST AI RMF, ISO 42001, and G-SIFI standards while evolving into a self-correcting, globally interoperable governance metabolism.</abstract>
<content><![CDATA[
# 1. The Civilizational AI Governance Stack: A Synthesis

## 1.1 AI Governance as Critical Infrastructure
By 2030, AI governance is no longer a corporate "add-on" but the **Regulated Critical Infrastructure** of the global intelligence economy. This stack aligns with:
- **NIST AI RMF 2.0 & ISO/IEC 42001**: Establishing the operational "Map, Measure, Manage" plane.
- **EU AI Act & GDPR**: Enforcing automated conformity and zero-trust data protection at the edge.
- **Basel III/IV & SR 11-7**: Mapping AGI reasoning to institutional model risk and capital adequacy.

## 1.2 The Terminal Governance Attractor
The "Terminal Attractor" is the architectural end-state where:
- **Memory**: The AuditorWORMVerifier ensures a perfect, immutable record of planetary reasoning.
- **Meaning**: The Civilizational Covenant Codex anchors all action to a shared set of human-aligned axioms.
- **Action**: High-assurance containment (Sentinel Core BMC) ensures all AGI swarms remain within the safety-envelope.
- **Legitimacy**: Formal verification and decentralized stewardship (ICGC) provide a regulator-defensible mandate for planetary intelligence.

## 1.3 Strategic Implications for Multilateral Bodies
The transition from AGI to ASI requires a "Governance Metabolism" that is both resilient and adaptive. The **Global Renewal Atlas** provides the multi-decade roadmap for the incremental release of capability, ensuring that human institutions can ingest and align new intelligence without catastrophic social or economic collapse.
]]></content>
</report>
