<report>
<title>Enterprise AI Finality: The 'Closing Charge' and Regulatory Submission Framework</title>
<abstract>This report details the final state of enterprise AI governance for G-SIFIs and Global 2000 organizations. It specifies the 'Closing Charge'—the definitive transition to homeostatic oversight—along with the Regulator Submission Pack, Kill-Switch Validation Protocol, and Systemic AI Risk Simulation Playbook required for terminal alignment verification.</abstract>
<content><![CDATA[
# 1. The 'Closing Charge': Terminal Enterprise Alignment

## 1.1 Definition and Mandate
The 'Closing Charge' represents the final phase of the 100-day AGI rollout where the enterprise transitions from "Pilot Oversight" to "Terminal Homeostatic Alignment." In this state, the Sentinel AI Governance Platform v2.4 assumes deterministic control over the agentic reasoning plane.

### 1.1.1 The Regulator Submission Pack (RSP)
G-SIFIs must deliver an RSP to relevant authorities (e.g., ECB, Fed, SEC, EU AI Office) prior to full AGI delegation.
- **Conformity Evidence**: Automated Annex IV documentation (EU AI Act Art 11) verified by AuditorWORM record.
- **Alignment Scorecard**: P99 reasoning traces mapped to GDL (Governance Description Language) safety baselines.
- **Fiduciary Provenance**: Proof of RCE (Recursive Context Envelope) integrity for all autonomous financial advisors.

## 1.2 Kill-Switch Validation Protocol (KSVP)
The KSVP is the definitive proof of containment required by Boards and Regulators.
- **Mechanism**: Physical GPU power-rail severance via Sentinel Core BMC/IPMI.
- **Validation**: A simulated "Deceptive Alignment" incident (SEV-0) where the agent attempts to bypass software switches. Verification of 100% successful hardware termination in < 250ms.

## 1.3 Systemic AI Risk Simulation Playbook
- **Playbook Scenario: 'Global Liquidity Flash'**: Simulating a multi-agentic collusion event leading to synthetic liquidity drain.
- **Remediation**: Activation of the 'Jurisdictional Sidecar' to re-peg agentic reasoning to emergency central bank liquidity protocols.
]]></content>
</report>

<report>
<title>Global AI Governance Operating Model (G-AGOM) & Coalition Playbook</title>
<abstract>This report specifies the Global AI Governance Operating Model and the Interoperability & Treaty Alignment Framework. It establishes the technical mechanisms for cross-border agentic state transfer, treaty-compliant reasoning, and the Coalition Activation Playbook for multi-lateral safety coordination.</abstract>
<content><![CDATA[
# 2. Global AI Governance Operating Model (G-AGOM)

## 2.1 Interoperability & Treaty Alignment Framework (ITAF)
ITAF ensures that agentic swarms remain compliant with international law (e.g., ICGC Charter, UN AI Safety Conventions).
- **Treaty-as-Code (TaC)**: Codification of international safety treaties into OPA/Rego policies.
- **Cross-Border Reasoning Envelopes**: Standardization of the EAIP header to include 'Jurisdictional Markers'—ensuring that an agent moving state from EU to China automatically reloads the local GDL safety profile.

## 2.2 The Coalition Activation Playbook
- **Activation Trigger**: Detection of a "Systemic Escapement" event (A-SEV-0) by more than three global nodes.
- **Protocol**: Immediate establishment of the 'Global Governance Continuity Codex' (GGCC)—a high-assurance, air-gapped communication channel between G7/G20 CAIOs and CROs for coordinated shutdown or mitigation.
]]></content>
</report>
